Today, I'm going to talk about the YouTube channel of Shokabo, a publisher specializing in natural science books
今天我要來聊聊裳華房這家自然科學書籍出版社的YouTube頻道
Huh? A publisher's channel? Is that what you're thinking?
咦？出版社的頻道？你是不是這樣想的？
But let me tell you, it's incredibly fascinating
但是這個頻道真的超級有趣
Shokabo's YouTube channel is truly wonderful
裳華房的YouTube頻道真的非常棒
If you're studying from science and engineering textbooks, this is a must-watch! I really want to recommend it
如果你是用理工科教科書學習的人，這絕對是必看的！我真的很想推薦給大家
And today, I want to introduce a mystery
今天我想介紹一個關於
about an unfinished masterpiece published by Shokabo
裳華房出版的未完成名著的神秘故事
Only the first volume was published
明明只出版了前篇
yet the first volume contains only the table of contents for the second volume
前篇裡卻只載有後篇的目錄
This is a very mysterious textbook
這是一本非常神秘的教科書
filled with the passionate thoughts of researchers and editors
承載著研究者和編輯的熱切心意
It's a truly moving story
這是一個非常感人的故事
So about today's video
那麼關於今天的影片
Surprisingly, this is NOT a promotion for Shokabo
令人驚訝的是，這並不是裳華房的業配
Yes, so introducing someone else's channel doesn't earn me a single yen
是的，所以介紹別人的頻道對我來說一毛錢都賺不到
But I wanted to express my gratitude for the work of publishers and editors who are essential for studying science and engineering
但是，我想對理工科學習不可或缺的出版社和編輯們的工作表達一點感謝
That's why I decided to make this video today
懷著這樣的心情，我決定製作今天的影片
So, won't you become a fan of Shokabo too?
所以，你也來成為裳華房的粉絲吧？
Now, for those who don't know what Shokabo is, let me give you a brief introduction
那麼，可能有些人不知道裳華房是什麼，讓我簡單介紹一下
Shokabo is a publisher of natural science books in physics, mathematics, and more
裳華房是一家出版物理、數學等自然科學書籍的出版社
On their official website, their mascot character Umeko-chan introduces their bestselling books and YouTube channel
在官方網站上，吉祥物梅子醬會介紹暢銷書籍和YouTube頻道
Umeko-chan is really cute, isn't she?
梅子醬真的很可愛對吧
So what kind of videos does Shokabo's YouTube channel have?
那麼裳華房的YouTube頻道有什麼樣的影片呢
First, there are lecture videos by the textbook authors themselves
首先有教科書作者親自講授的講座影片
Professor Junichiro Kishine from The Open University of Japan
放送大學的岸根順一郎老師
has published a thermodynamics textbook through Shokabo
透過裳華房出版了熱力學教科書
and amazingly, the professor himself appears
而且教授本人親自出演
to give thermodynamics lectures
為大家講授熱力學課程
You could say the publisher is also in the business of debuting researchers as YouTubers
可以說出版社也在經營讓研究者出道成為YouTuber的事業
That's one way to look at it
也可以這樣來看待
And this is today's main topic
而這就是今天的主題
There are videos where editors share behind-the-scenes stories
有編輯分享幕後故事的影片
These are really fascinating
這個真的非常有趣
You might think that a YouTube channel from a physics and math publisher
你可能會覺得物理和數學書籍出版社的YouTube頻道
would just be some boring corporate promotional channel, but
只是一個無聊的企業宣傳頻道吧
That's not the case at all!
完全不是那樣！
Behind the publishing of natural science books lies a grand drama
自然科學書籍出版的背後有著壯闘的故事
Watching this reminded me of "The Great Passage"
看到這個讓我想起了《乘舟編舟》
I believe it's no exaggeration to say that Shokabo's YouTube is like a science version of "The Great Passage"
我認為說裳華房的YouTube是理科版的《乘舟編舟》一點也不為過
Let me briefly explain "The Great Passage"
讓我簡單說明一下《乘舟編舟》
It's a novel by Shion Miura
這是三浦紫苑老師的小說
that won the Booksellers' Award in 2012
2012年獲得本屋大賞的作品
The story is about publishing a Japanese dictionary
這是一個以國語辭典出版為題材的故事
and was a hit as a movie, anime, and drama
電影、動畫、電視劇都非常賣座
Editors and linguists work together
編輯和國語學者合作
to create a Japanese dictionary
一起製作國語辭典
It's a superb intellectual entertainment
是一部極上的知識娛樂作品
I think one of the themes of "The Great Passage" is
我認為《乘舟編舟》這部作品的主題之一
passing on one's work and way of life to future generations
就是將自己的工作和生活方式傳承給後世
Publishing a Japanese dictionary is a massive project
國語辭典的出版是一個大型專案
In the story, 13 years pass
在故事中竟然經過了13年的時間
That's how long such work takes
這就是這種工作需要的漫長時間
Over 13 years, naturally the characters' life stages change
13年過去，登場人物們的人生階段當然也會改變
Some get married, senior employees retire or pass away
有人結婚，年長的員工退休或者過世
And through all this, various forms of succession are depicted, I believe
而在其中描繪了各種形式的傳承，我是這樣認為的
And the exact same thing
而完全相同的事情
can be seen in Shokabo's YouTube channel
在裳華房的YouTube頻道也可以看到
Especially in the video I'm introducing today, you can feel this strongly
特別是在今天介紹的影片中，這種感覺尤為強烈
The main video I especially want to recommend
今天我特別想推薦的
from Shokabo is this one
裳華房的影片是這個
The Unfinished Masterpiece
未完成的名著
The Secret Left in the First Volume
留在前篇中的○○秘密
And speaking about the passion for academic book editing
以及講述學術書籍編輯熱情的
Connecting Knowledge
連結知識
The title "Unfinished Masterpiece" is intriguing, isn't it?
光是「未完成的名著」這個標題就很吸引人對吧
The video features
這部影片介紹的是
Professor Isao Imai's "Fluid Mechanics (Volume 1)" textbook
今井功教授的《流體力學（前篇）》這本教科書
This book was first published in 1973 and is still being reprinted as a masterpiece
這本書1973年初版，至今仍在再版的名著
There's also an e-book version, so you can have it without taking up shelf space
也有電子版，所以不用佔用書架空間就能擁有，這也是它的魅力
But this book has a big mystery
但是這本書有一個很大的謎團
The title says "Volume 1" but Volume 2 doesn't exist
標題寫著前篇，但後篇卻不存在
Professor Imai passed away without ever writing Volume 2
今井功教授在沒有寫完後篇的情況下就過世了
But there's something even more mysterious
但還有更不可思議的事情
This first volume contains the table of contents for the non-existent second volume
這本前篇裡載有不存在的後篇的目錄
Look at this
請看這個
Volume 2 doesn't exist, yet there's a clear outline of what was planned
後篇不存在，但原本計畫要寫什麼
Only the table of contents remains
目錄卻清楚地保留下來了
Boundary layers, turbulence, magnetohydrodynamics
邊界層、亂流、電磁流體等等
Various topics are listed
列出了各種主題
I want to read about all of them...
每個都想讀……
But there's no Volume 2
但是沒有後篇
Yet it's still being published as "Volume 1"
卻至今仍以前篇之名出版
Some readers say
有些讀者說
if Volume 2 isn't coming out, the table of contents shouldn't be there
如果後篇不會出版，目錄就不應該留著
I've heard there are people with that opinion
聽說有人持這樣的意見
I can certainly understand that feeling
確實能理解那種心情
There were really many voices of expectation from readers
讀者的期待聲音真的很多
Mr. Ono, an editor at Shokabo who appears in the video
影片中出現的裳華房編輯小野先生
said that when he was a young employee answering the company phone
說他年輕時在公司接電話的時候
he received so many calls asking "When will Volume 2 of Professor Imai's Fluid Mechanics come out?"
經常接到「今井老師的流體力學後篇什麼時候出版？」的詢問
There were really so many inquiries
真的非常多這樣的詢問
He said there were times when he was afraid of the phone ringing
他說有段時間很害怕電話響起
So why does this table of contents remain?
那麼為什麼這個目錄會一直保留著呢
This mystery is revealed in the video
這個謎團在影片中揭曉
Editor Ono shares the story of his last meeting with Professor Imai
編輯小野先生講述了他最後一次見到今井教授時的故事
Mr. Ono visited Professor Imai's home many times
小野先生多次前往今井教授的家
asking "How is the manuscript for Volume 2 coming along?"
詢問「後篇的稿子進展如何？」
Professor Imai was already in his 80s at that time
今井教授當時已經80多歲高齡
and must have been struggling physically and health-wise
體力和健康狀況應該都很艱難
Yet Mr. Ono had to follow up on the manuscript as part of his job
但小野先生作為工作還是必須催促稿件
You can feel his difficulty in doing so
可以感受到他的為難
And the last time Mr. Ono met Professor Imai
而小野先生最後一次見到今井教授時
the professor said this
教授這樣說道
"I'm truly sorry that I couldn't publish Volume 2"
「真的很抱歉沒能出版後篇」
"However..." What did Professor Imai say after this?
「不過……」今井教授之後說了什麼
Please watch the full video to find out
請一定要看影片本篇
Professor Imai's conviction as a researcher
今井教授作為研究者的信念
Mr. Ono's sense of mission as an editor
小野先生作為編輯的使命感
You can feel them both
都能深深感受到
I was deeply moved
我真的非常感動
The table of contents for the non-existent Volume 2
這個不存在的後篇的目錄
is not just a table of contents
不只是一個目錄
It represents Professor Imai's passion for fluid mechanics itself
它代表了今井教授對流體力學的熱情本身
You could say it's homework that Professor Imai left for us
可以說這是今井教授留給我們的作業
That's why this table of contents remains to this day
所以這個目錄至今仍然保留著
I was moved to see that this is the work of editors, the unsung heroes of knowledge transmission
這讓我深深感動，這就是作為知識傳承幕後功臣的編輯的工作
We can still read books published over 50 years ago thanks to the work of editors
我們能夠讀到50多年前出版的書籍，都是托編輯們工作的福
We tend to think that human knowledge has progressed continuously throughout history
我們往往認為人類的知識隨著歷史的發展不斷進步
But that's not true at all. Historically, much knowledge has been lost
但其實完全不是這樣，歷史上有許多失落的知識
For example, the Library of Alexandria. This library was built in the 3rd century BC in what is now Alexandria, Egypt, and housed various books recording the knowledge of Greek civilization at the time. However, this library lost a vast amount of knowledge due to financial difficulties and wars.
例如亞歷山大圖書館。這座圖書館建於西元前3世紀，位於現在埃及的亞歷山大，收藏了記錄當時希臘文明知識的各種書籍，但這座圖書館因財政困難和戰亂等原因失去了大量知識。
A more familiar example would be broken links to references in blog posts from 10 years ago. Even events from just 10 years ago are difficult to trace accurately now
更貼近生活的例子是10年前部落格文章中的參考文獻連結。即使只是10年前的事情，現在也很難準確追溯
Knowledge is easily lost without effort to maintain it. Publishers and editors do the tremendously important work of passing knowledge on to the next generation
知識如果不努力維護，很容易就會失去。出版社和編輯從事著將知識傳承給下一代這項極其重要的工作
Shokabo's channel has many other truly valuable stories
裳華房的頻道還有很多其他珍貴的故事
For example, Professor Ryogo Kubo's "Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics"
例如久保亮五教授的《熱學・統計力學》
commonly known as "Kubo Statistics"
通稱「久保統計」的教科書
There's also a video introducing its behind-the-scenes story
也有介紹其幕後故事的影片
This was first published in 1961
這本書1961年出版
and a revised edition came out in 1998. It's a masterpiece among masterpieces
1998年出了修訂版，是名著中的名著
Mr. Ono was involved in editing the revised edition
小野先生參與了修訂版的編輯工作
"The Complete Solutions to Kubo Statistics" - anyone who has studied physics
「久保統計的完全解答」——任何學過物理的人
would get excited
聽到都會熱血沸騰
or get chills at this topic. The episodes about it
或者背脊發涼的話題。關於這個的故事
are explained in a way that even those unfamiliar with Kubo Statistics can understand
即使是不了解久保統計的人也能輕鬆理解
There are stories about mishaps when entertaining professors at the revised edition release
有修訂版出版時招待教授們時的出糗故事
and about how editor Ono sent a complaint postcard to Shokabo about a textbook when he was a student
還有編輯小野先生學生時代曾用明信片向裳華房投訴教科書的問題
only to end up reading his own complaint postcard after joining the company
結果進公司後竟然讀到了自己寫的投訴明信片
These human-interest episodes make it very relatable
這些充滿人情味的故事，讓人感到非常親切
It's really full of highlights
真的是精彩滿滿
So if you've become even a little interested in Shokabo's YouTube channel
那麼如果你對裳華房的YouTube頻道產生了一點興趣
please check out the actual videos
請一定要去看看實際的影片
If you'd like
如果可以的話
please subscribe to Shokabo's YouTube channel and give them a like
請訂閱裳華房YouTube頻道並按讚
I'd really appreciate it
拜託了
Why am I asking you to subscribe and like
為什麼我不是請大家訂閱自己的頻道
someone else's channel instead of my own?
而是請大家訂閱別人的頻道按讚呢
Well, it doesn't earn me anything
唉，這對我來說一點好處都沒有
But it's truly wonderful content
但這真的是非常棒的內容
so I really hope you'll watch it
所以真的希望大家能看看
See you in the next video. Take care!
那麼下次影片再見，保重！